ALIN TOMESCU

PERSONAL INFORMATION

email atom@alum.mit.edu

website http://alinush.org

github https://github.com/alinush

twitter https://twitter.com/alinush407

SHORT BIO

I am interested in applied cryptography, mostly walking the fine line between theory and practice. In the past, I've worked on oblivious RAMs, public-key distribution, authenticated data structures, and threshold cryptography. I especially enjoy implementing and open-sourcing my work. In the present, I am working on anonymous payments, vector commitmments, verifiable secret sharing and distributed key generation.

I sometimes blog about my work and muse about other things on my website.

For paper LaTeX and PDFs, slides, code artifacts and talk videos, please see alinush.github.io/papers.html.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2021-2022 Aptos Labs

Research Scientist Working on applied cryptography for high-throughput smart contract

blockchains.

2021-2022 VMware Research

Research Scientist Working on anonymous payments and authenticated data structures.

2020-2021 VMware Research

Postdoctoral Researcher Worked on aggregatable and maintainable vector commitments, RSA-based authenticated dictionaries, aggregatable distributed key generation, and other

applied cryptography topics.

Summer 2017 VMware Research

& 2018

Research Intern Worked on multi-party computation protocols via verfiable secret sharing.

Worked on scaling byzantine fault tolerance protocols using threshold signatures. Implemented a fast C++ library for RSA and BLS threshold signatures. Designed efficient anonymous cryptocurrencies without

zk-SNARKs.

Mentors: Ittai Авканам and Dahlia Мацки

2013-2020 MIT CSAIL

Research Assistant Focused on cryptocurrencies, public-key distribution, authenticated data

structures, secure communication, anonymity and secure web applications.

Lab: Computation Structures Group Advisor: Prof. Srinivas Devadas

2011-2012 STONY BROOK UNIVERSITY

Research Assistant Worked on access pattern privacy research.

Developed PrivateFS, the first oblivious filesystem.

Lab: Network Security and Applied Crypto Lab

Advisor: Prof. Radu Sion

EDUCATION

2015-2019 Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Doctor of Philosophy

School: Electrical Engineering and Computer Science

Thesis: How to Keep a Secret and Share a Public Key (Using Polynomial

Commitments)

Advisor: Prof. Srinivas Devadas

2013-2015 Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Masters of Science

GPA: 4.7 (out of 5) · Major: Computer Science Thesis: *PowMail: Want To Fork? Do Some Work.*

Description: This thesis explored the idea of using cryptographic puzzles computed by email users to prevent equivocation in public key directories.

Advisor: Prof. Srinivas Devadas

2008-2012 Stony Brook University

Bachelors of Science

GPA: 3.98 (out of 4) · Major: Computer Science

Summa Cum Laude · Honors Advisor: Associate Prof. Radu Sion

WORK EXPERIENCE

2012-2013,

Summer 2014

Private Machines

Head of Research and Development

Designed, implemented and deployed the first prototype of the CipherRack secure cloud infrastructure.

Designed and implemented cryptographic protocols for CipherLocker, a secure searchable cloud file storage engine, as well as other proprietary cryptographic protocols.

Summer 2011 MICROSOFT

Software Development Engineer in Test (Intern)

Developed a flexible performance framework in C# for testing critical Microsoft SQL stored procedures used throughout their AdCenter Business Intelligence system.

Daniela.

Developed an ASP .NET user interface in C# for charting and graphing performance results across release cycles.

Developed an automated code deployment tool for running daily basic viability tests on the latest builds.

2008–2009 Stony Brook University

Information Technology Specialist Developed websites for various programs within the Outreach Division of

 $Stony\ Brook's\ Professional\ Education\ Program.$

Developed and maintained Microsoft Access databases. Created and administered LISTSERV mailing lists. Assisted staff with various computer-related issues.

MANUSCRIPTS

Hyperproofs: Aggregating and Maintaining Proofs in Vector Commitments · ePrint'21 · Shravan Srinivasan, Alex Chepurnoy, Charalampos Papamanthou, Alin Tomescu, Yupeng Zhang

Authenticated Dictionaries with Cross-Incremental Proof (Dis)aggregation · ePrint'20 · Charalampos Papamanthou, Alin Tomescu, Yu Xia, Zachary Newman

How to compute all Pointproofs \cdot ePrint'20 \cdot Alin Tomescu

PUBLICATIONS

Hyperproofs: Aggregating and Maintaining Proofs in Vector Commitments · USENIX Security'22 · Shravan Srinivasan, Alex Chepurnoy, Charalampos Papamanthou, Alin Tomescu, Yupeng Zhang

Reaching Consensus for Asynchronous Distributed Key Generation \cdot PODC'21 \cdot Ittai Abraham, Philipp Jovanovic, Mary Maller, Sarah Meiklejohn, Gilad Stern, Alin Tomescu

Aggregatable Distributed Key Generation · EUROCRYPT'21 · Kobi Gurkan, Philipp Jovanovic, Mary Maller, Sarah Meiklejohn, Gilad Stern, Alin Tomescu

Aggregatable Subvector Commitments for Stateless Cryptocurrencies \cdot SCN'20 \cdot Alin Tomescu, Ittai Abraham, Vitalik Buterin, Justin Drake, Dankrad Feist, Dmitry Khovratovich

Towards Scalable Threshold Cryptosystems \cdot IEEE S&P'20 \cdot Alin Tomescu, Robert Chen, Yiming Zehng, Ittai Abraham, Benny Pinkas, Guy Golan Gueta, Srinivas Devadas

Transparency Logs via Append-only Authenticated Dictionaries · ACM CCS'19 · Alin Tomescu, Vivek Bhupatiraju, Dimitrios Papadopoulos, Charalampos Papamanthou, Nikos Triandopoulos, Srinivas Devadas

Efficient Verifiable Secret Sharing with Share Recovery in BFT Protocols · ACM CCS'19 · Soumya Basu, Alin Tomescu, Ittai Авганам, Dahlia Malkhi, Michael K. Reiter, Emin Gün Sirer

SBFT: A Scalable and Decentralized Trust Infrastructure · DSN'19 · Guy Golan Gueta, Ittai Abraham, Shelly Grossman, Dahlia Malkhi, Benny Pinkas, Michael K. Reiter, Dragos-Adrian Seredinschi, Orr Tamir, Alin Tomescu

Catena: Efficient Non-equivocation via Bitcoin · IEEE S&P'17 · Alin Tomescu, Srinivas Devadas

 $PriviPK: Certificate-less \ and \ secure \ email \ communication \cdot Computer \ \& \ Security'17 \cdot Mashael \ Alsabah, \ Alin \ Tomescu, \ Ilia \ Lebedev, \ Dimitrios \ Serpanos, \ Srini \ Devadas$

 $PrivateFS: A \ Parallel \ Oblivious \ Filesystem \cdot \ ACM \ CCS'12 \cdot Peter \ Williams, \ Radu \ Sion, \ Alin \ Tomescu$

PATENTS

Two-round byzantine fault tolerant (BFT) state machine replication (SMR) protocol with linear authenticator complexity and optimistic responsiveness \cdot US Patent App \cdot June 2021 Ittai Abraham, Alin Tomescu, Guy Golan Gueta, Neil Giridharan, Heidi Howard

Byzantine fault tolerance with verifiable secret sharing at constant overhead · US
Patent US10572352B2 · Feb. 25th, 2020 · Soumya Basu, Alin Tomescu, Dahlia
Malkhi, Michael Reiter, Adrian Seredinschi, Ittai Abraham, Guy Golan Gueta

INVITED TALKS

Some recordings can be found here.

Hyperproofs: Aggregating and Maintaining Proofs in Vector Commitments \cdot Protocol Labs \cdot May 28th, 2021

 $\textit{Hyperproofs: Aggregating and Maintaining Proofs in Vector Commitments} \cdot Cornell \\ \textit{University} \cdot \textit{April 8th, 2021}$

Hyperproofs: Aggregating and Maintaining Proofs in Vector Commitments \cdot Cornell University \cdot March 24th, 2021

 $\textit{Vector Commitments for Stateless Cryptocurrencies} \cdot \text{Duke University} \cdot \text{Privacy \& Security Seminar} \cdot \text{March 9th, 2021}$

Towards Scalable Threshold Cryptosystems · Real World Decentralized Cryptography · January 15th, 2021

Authenticated Data Structures for Stateless Validation and Transparency logs · University College London · InfoSec Seminar · November 5th, 2020

Authenticated Dictionaries with Cross-incremental Proof (Dis)aggregation · zkStudyClub · October 28th, 2020

Towards Scalable Threshold Cryptosystems · Cornell University · June, 2020

Aggregatable Subvector Commitments · zkStudyClub · May 13th, 2020

Towards Scalable Threshold Cryptosystems \cdot BU Security Seminar \cdot Boston University \cdot January 29th, 2020

Append-only Authenticated Dictionaries and Their Applications · MIT Digital Currency Initiative · March 27th, 2019

Append-only Authenticated Dictionaries and Their Applications \cdot Xi'an International Workshop on Blockchain 2018 \cdot December 14th, 2018

Append-only Authenticated Dictionaries and Their Applications · Modular Approach to Cloud Security (MACS) Project Meeting · December 7th, 2018

Bandwidth-efficient Transparency Logs via Append-only Authenticated Dictionaries · VISA Research · July 13th, 2018

Bandwidth-efficient Transparency Logs via Append-only Authenticated Dictionaries · Stanford Security Seminar · Stanford University · June 26th, 2018

Append-only Authenticated Dictionaries and Their Applications \cdot Oasis Labs \cdot June 21st, 2018

Append-only Authenticated Dictionaries and Their Applications · LPD · École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL) · January 31st, 2018

Catena: Efficient Non-equivocation via $Bitcoin \cdot Cambridge Blockchain Meetup \cdot December 13th, 2017$

Append-only Authenticated Dictionaries and Their Applications · Security Reading Group · University of Maryland · October 27th, 2017

Secure communication via proof-of-work \cdot CSAIL Advisory Board \cdot MIT \cdot May 3rd, 2016

Pulsar: A Space and Bandwidth Efficient, Trustworthy Public Key Directory \cdot Digital Currency Initiative (DCI) \cdot MIT \cdot April 6th, 2016

ACCEPTED TALKS

Catena: Preventing Lies with Bitcoin \cdot New England Security Day (NESD) \cdot Worcester Polytechnic Institute \cdot November 28th, 2016

PANELS

On "blockchains" · TechConnect · Boston University · February 16th, 2018

OPEN SOURCE CONTRIBUTIONS

QEMU · Eucalyptus · RELIC · Concord BFT · libfqfft

PROGRAM COMMITTEES

ACM Advances in Financial Technologies (AFT) · 2021

ACM Cloud Computing Security Workshop (CCSW) · 2020 · 2021

ACM Conference on Computer and Communication Security (CCS) \cdot 2021 \cdot 2022

Financial Cryptography (FC) · 2021

IEEE Security & Privacy (Oakland) · 2023

USENIX Security · 2022

VMware R&D Innovation Offsite (RADIO) · 2022

EXTERNAL REVIEWER

ACM Advances in Financial Technologies (AFT) · 2020 · 2022

ACM Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS) \cdot 2017

ACM ASIA Conference on Computer and Communication Security (AsiaCCS) \cdot 2020

ACM Conference on Computer and Communication Security (CCS) \cdot 2016 \cdot 2020

ACM Symposium on Principles of Distributed Computing (PODC) \cdot 2021 \cdot 2022

IACR ASIACRYPT · 2020

IACR CRYPTO · 2021

IACR Security and Cryptography for Networks (SCN) · 2016

IACR TCC · 2021

IEEE Security and Privacy (S&P) · 2018 · 2019 · 2020

IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics & Security (TIFS) \cdot 2021

IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO) \cdot 2017

Network and Distributed Systems Symposium (NDSS) · 2019

Transactions on Privacy and Security (TOPS) · 2017 · 2019

USENIX Security · 2023

TEACHING & MENTORING

Guest Lectures

Duke University · Fall 2021 · CS590.02: Cryptocurrency and Cryptography · Aggregatable, Maintainable and Unstealable Vector Commitments

MIT · Spring 2018 · MAS.S62 Cryptocurrency Engineering and Design · Bitcoin-based non-equivocation schemes · YouTube

2017-2019 MIT PRIMES

Research Mentor

Mentored 4 high school students in applied cryptography research. Planned reasonable research projects for students with deliverables. Met with students weekly to assess progress and discuss research topics.

Student Awards:

John Kuszmaul · 2017 Siemens semifinalist Robert Chen · 2017 Siemens semifinalist YIMING ZHENG · 2017 Siemens semifinalist VIVEK BHUPATIRAJU · 2018 Regeneron STS scholar

VIVEK BHUPATIRAJU · 2018 ISEF 3rd Special Award (from ACM)

VIVEK BHUPATIRAJU · 2018 ISEF 1st Special Award (Science of Security, from

NSA)

ROBERT CHEN · 2019 Regeneron STS scholar

Spring 2014 Introduction to Algorithms (6.006)

Teaching Assistant at MIT

Taught four recitation sessions each week.

Taught two review sessions before midterm exams.

Developed programming assignments for the problem sets.

Wrote recitation notes for students.

Developed questions for the student exams.

Helped students on the class discussion board and over email.

Held biweekly office hours.

Provided additional learning resources for my own section students.

Spring 2011 ADVANCED C/C++ PROGRAMMING (CSE230)

Teaching Assistant at Stony Brook University Taught four CSE230 lectures on object oriented design in C++.

Helped students with C and C++ programming questions during officer

hours.

Fall 2009 Introduction to Java (CSE114)

Teaching Assistant at Stony Brook University $Held\ biweekly, one-hour\ and\ twenty-minutes\ programming\ labs.$

Responsible for overseeing, teaching and grading thirty students in CSE114.

Helped and advised students during office hours and over email.

2009–2012 Stony Brook Computing Society

Exam Reviewer

Taught review sessions for Java programming, discrete mathematics and data structures exams.

OTHER INFORMATION

Awards

Best Reviewer Award · ACM CCS · 2021

Avery Ashdown Leadership Award · Ashdown House, MIT · 2015 & 2019

Academic Excellence in Computer Science \cdot Computer Science Department at Stony Brook University \cdot 2012

The SUNY Chancellor's Award for Student Excellence \cdot State University of New York (SUNY) \cdot 2012

Undergraduate Recognition Award for Academic Excellence \cdot Stony Brook University \cdot 2012

Outstanding Academic Achievement Award · Stony Brook University · 2009–2012

University Scholars Senior Leadership Award · Stony Brook University · 2011

February 2011 Student of the Month Award \cdot National Residence Hall Honorary Chapter at Stony Brook University \cdot 2011

Leadership

Graduate Student Leadership Initiative Fellow & Cambridge Fellow · *Massachusetts Institute of Technology* · Spring 2017

Secretary of the Ashdown House Executive Committee \cdot *Massachusetts Institute of Technology* \cdot 2014–2015

President of the Romanian Student Association \cdot Massachusetts Institute of Technology \cdot 2014–2019

Student Ambassador for the Stony Brook Computer Science Department \cdot *Stony Brook University* \cdot 2011–2012

Cofounder, Vice-President and President of the Stony Brook Game Developers Club \cdot Stony Brook University \cdot 2009–2010

Communication

Best Computer Science Senior Honors Project Presentation Award \cdot Stony Brook

University · 2012

Languages

Interests

Skills

Romanian · Native language

English · Fluent

 $S_{\text{PANISH}} \qquad \cdot \text{ Basic (simple words and phrases only)} \\ F_{\text{RENCH}} \qquad \cdot \text{ Basic (simple words and phrases only)}$

Piano · Philosophy · Weightlifting · Dance

June 17, 2022